So over the last lectures we had a look at a lot of possible next steps including libraries like Gatsbyjs
Bu yzden son derslerde Gatsbyjs gibi ktphaneler veya Material-UI gibi bileen ktphaneleri de dahil
or component libraries like Material-UI.
olmak zere bir ok olas aamaya bir gz attk.
Here's one other nice library you might want to look into,
Bakmak isteyebileceiniz bir tane
preact. Now that's no typo, preact which you can read more about on preactjs.com is a lightweight
gzel ktphane, preact. imdi bu preactjs hakknda daha fazla okuyabileceiniz bir yazm hatas, preact. com, tepki vermek iin
alternative to react,
hafif bir alternatiftir,
it's only 3kb big and it offers pretty much the same with some deviations but not that many
sadece 3kb byktr ve baz sapmalarla hemen hemen ayndr ancak pek ok
API react does. So should you always use that,
API tepkisi yoktur. Her zaman bunu kullanmal mydn,
are the creators of react stupid?
aptalca tepkilerin yaratclar m?
They are not,
Onlar deil, farkllklar var
there are differences and I will talk about these in the next lecture but for now, let me explain what
ve bir sonraki derste bunlardan bahsedeceim, ama imdilik, hangi preact olduunu aklamama
preact is,
izin ver,
you could always read through this page of course but let's click on the repl here, on that page.
tabii ki bu sayfadan okuyabiliyorsun, ama bu sayfada, buraya tklatalm.
There you simply see an example for the preact or for preact in action
Orada sadece preact veya preact eylem iin bir rnek
and if you analyzed this example, you'll recognize the code.
gryorsunuz ve bu rnei analiz ettiyseniz, kodu tanyacaksnz.
For example down there, we have a normal component in the functional form just using destructuring here
Mesela, burada, sadece props argmannn bir zelliini karmak iin burada ykmn kullanlmasn salayan fonksiyonel
to pull out one property of the props argument
bir formda normal bir bileene sahibiz, ama
but in the end that's just your normal jsx code,
sonunda sadece normal jsx kodunuz,
that's just a functional component which gets used. And above and we got a class based one which also extends
bu da kullanlmakta olan ilevsel bir bileen. Ve yukarda ve ayrca bileeni
component,
genileten
so this syntax looks a lot like react syntax and it is to a majority or to a certain degree, to a very
bir snf temelli var, bu yzden bu szdizimi tepki szdizimine ok benziyor ve byk lde
big degree actually. Preact uses pretty much the same API but uses a leaner diffing algorithm behind
ya da byk lde belli bir dereceye kadar. Preact, hemen hemen ayn API'yi kullanr ancak sahnelerin ardnda bir yaln
the scenes,
farkl algoritma
so for finding out if it needs to update the real dom, it has a leaner algorithm for that.
kullanr, bylece gerek dom gncellemesinin gerekip gerekmediini renmek iin bunun iin daha yaln bir algoritma vardr.
Lean doesn't strictly mean better but of course it leads to a much smaller file size, 3kb
Yaln kesinlikle daha iyi anlamna gelmez, ancak size gsterdiim gibi 3kb daha
as I just showed you. The important thing here is that preact and you can always learn more here on
kk bir dosya boyutuna yol aar. Burada nemli olan preact ve rehber hakknda her zaman
the guide
daha fazla
also offers some differences to react, even some new features as it will turn out
bilgi edinebilirsiniz, ayn zamanda tepki vermek iin baz farkllklar, hatta baz yeni zellikler ortaya kacak ama
but more about the differences in the next lecture.
bir sonraki dersteki farkllklar hakknda daha fazla bilgi verecektir.
You can start working with preact, if you google for preact-cli, then you should find this github page where
Eer preact-cli iin google eer, preact ile almaya balayabilirsiniz, o zaman aka tepki vermek yerine preact kullanan
you find a project which is a lot like create react app which allows you to create new preact apps
yeni preact uygulamalar oluturmanza olanak salar tepki uygulamas oluturmak ok gibi bir proje bulmak nerede
which use preact instead of react
bu github sayfasn bulmak
obviously, based on some of the templates you find here. So you can quickly scaffold out a new app where
gerekir Burada bulduunuz baz ablonlara dayanarak. Bylece, bu derste rendiiniz eylerin ounu
you can use the majority of the things you learned in this course, again differences are highlighted
kullanabileceiniz yeni bir uygulamay hzlca yaplandrabilirsiniz, bir sonraki derste farkllklar n
in the next lecture and simply use this much smaller bundle, this much smaller library.
plana karlr ve bu ok daha kk bir ktphane olan ok daha kk bir kitaplk kullanlr.
This is preact-cli and this is preact, a lightweight alternative using pretty much the same API and
Bu preact-cli'dir ve bu, hemen hemen ayn API'yi kullanan hafif bir alternatiftir ve
therefore, the things you learned in this course are valid.
bu nedenle, bu derste rendiiniz eyler geerlidir.
Now let's find out what the differences are then and when you should and should not use react,
imdi o zaman farklarn ne olduunu ve tepkisini ne zaman kullanacanz ve kullanmamay renelim,
let's do this in the next lecture.
bunu bir sonraki derste yapalm.